<resources>
    <string name="app_name">VisitLorrha</string>
    <string name="title_activity_maps">Map</string>
    <string name="title_activity_photosphere">Photosphere</string>
    <string name="title_activity_maps_activity_augustinian_abbey">Map</string>
    <string name="title_activity_maps_activity_st_ruadhans_abbey">Map</string>
    <string name="title_activity_maps_activity_lackeen_castle">Map</string>

    <string name="textInformationdominicanabbey"> The Dominican Friary is located beside the present
        day Roman Catholic Church. It was founded in 1269 by Walter De Burgo, Earl of Ulster and a major
        local landowner, who was of the Burkes that were to settle in nearby Portumna Castle. The
        Dominican Order was founded in 1215 by St. Dominic; their rules were based on poverty and preaching.
        They wore a black cloak and hood over a white tunic; hence they were often referred to as the
        ‘Black Friars’. The order came to Ireland in 1224 and by 1300 had 24 friaries, Lorrha of course
        being one of these.One can only imagine the life of a friar down through the centuries, their strict
        lifestyles consisting of hours of silent prayer, long periods of fasting and working to provide for
        and maintain their upkeep. They would have worked the mill (still situated beside the Friary) on the
        banks of the Lorrha River which would have provided bread, a most important part of people’s diet in
        those days. Anyone passing by the Friary might also have become accustomed to the sound of numerous
        holy men chanting and singing from their various psalms. They might also leave their quarters to preach
        to the local people who in those times were still hanging on to the old pre-Christian beliefs and were
        often at war with neighbouring territories. The friars would have had living quarters close to the main
        building of worship and there is structural evidence that these might have been situated under the
        Roman Catholic Church. A statue of St. Ruadhan is believed to have been situated in a niche in the
        south wall and is suggested to have been carved from wood; no trace of it remains today. Also inside
        the church and placed on the wall are grave slab memorials of two important families of Lorrha’s past,
        the O’Kennedys and the McEgans. There is evidence the monastery was burned at one time with traces of
        smoke staining under the large window at the east gable. Cromwell’s army is believed to be responsible
        for this. and as Lorrha was on their path as they marched from Athlone to Limerick it is most probable
        that the Friary would not have escaped their ‘fire and sword’. The Monastery seems to have survived the
        Cromwellian campaign of the 1650’s and the dissolution of the monasteries in 1537.
    </string>
    <string name="textInformationaugustinianabbey"> A much more welcome and peaceful group of newcomers arrived
        in Lorrha in the 12th century, these were the priors who were devoted to Saint Augustine. The priors
        would have lived to the saints often controversial teachings which were known as the rules of Saint
        Augustine. They dressed in black cloaks and were often known as `Black Canons’. On the top of the ornate
        doorway on the south wall is the carved head of a woman wearing a horned headdress, one suggestion is
        that this lady was the wife of the Norman overlord who might have commissioned its building as was normal
        practice in those days. The Priory also held a piscina with credence. The piscina was a small carved
        stone basin used for washing the communion vessels and the credence was an ornate shelf that supported
        the piscina. These two items were removed in the 1880`s and brought to the Church of the Immaculate
        Conception in Minneapolis. One James McGoldrick, who was Bishop of Minneapolis at the time, was
        originally from nearby Aglish. He was a frequent visitor to his homestead at the time and he presumably
        brought the items back with him from one of his visits. The priory lasted in Lorrha for over 400 years
        and one prior in particular had a gruesome fate in the late 16th century!
    </string>
    <string name="textInformationstruadhansabbey"> St. Ruadhan was first to put Lorrha on the map coming here
        in the middle of the 6th century. He was educated in Clonard Co. Westmeath by St. Finian and was known
        as one of the Twelve Apostles of Ireland. He is said to have replaced St. Brendan (the navigator) at
        Lorrha who preceded to cross the Shannon and set up his monastery at Clonfert Co. Galway Ruadhan founded
        a monastic settlement here that would have consisted of a monastery and various other buildings
        including cells for the many monks that would have lived here. Also a ditch or large mound would have
        been built around the settlement to keep animals in and intruders out, the outlines of these are still
        visible today. Life for the monks would have been tough but simple, rising early from their beds which
        would have consisted of rushes or straw placed on the bare ground. They then would pray and fast between
        their domestic chores. The settlement would have been self sufficient in those days providing everything
        from food, clothing, to shelter. On the site of this settlement are the remains of an 11th century church
        probably on the spot of Ruadhan’s original monastery. It has at the west end of the south wall an ornate
        doorway that shows many carved motifs including a pelican drawing blood from its breast. Also there are
        the remains of two high crosses with only the decorated shafts remaining, one of these is said to mark
        the grave of a Munster king who died at Lorrha, the other is said to mark St. Ruadhan’s grave although
        it seems to have been crafted many years after his death. Villages and towns often popped up around monastic
        settlements as trade and refuge attracted the local people, the origin of Lorrha village can be attributed
        to this. There are many legends attributed to Ruadhan but he is probably most famous for his curse on the
        High King’s residence at Tara after the king, Diarmuid Mac Cerbhaill, had violated the sanctity of the church
        by taken a hostage from its protection. The downfall of Tara from a once thriving royal residence is
        credited to Ruadhan. The bell of St. Ruadhan which was found in a well named after the Saint is kept in
        the British Museum after being discovered many years ago. This well is situated across the road from the
        present day Church of Ireland. “My splendid cloak adorned with gold which was on the altar of Rome, bring
        it to Ruadhan of Lortha, since we shall die this day” extract from the last will and testament of the high
        king of Cashel.
    </string>
    <string name="textInformationlackeencastle"> This tower house was constructed in the 16th century by Brian O’Kennedy,
        who was head of the O’Kennedy Fionn (fair) branch of the clan at the time. A defensive wall known as a bawn surrounds
        the castle that remains in remarkably good condition, this is helped by the fact that a roof remained on
        the building up to recent times preventing corrosion and weathering. Lackeen was an O’Kennedy stronghold
        of Lower Ormond and would have been a bustling centre of activity in the 16th century. There are the remains
        of a mill by the river at Lackeen and a village known as Piperstown was recorded as having been on the O’Kennedys
        estate although all traces of it have disappeared over the centuries. The O’Kennedys lost possession of the castle
        and estate that stretched over 1,000 acres in the 1650’s; this was due to the Cromwellian confiscations. The
        owner of Lackeen at the time was Donogh O’Kennedy who was subsequently transferred to Connaught; he received a
        much smaller and lesser valuable estate in Clonfert Co. Galway. The O’Kennedys must have regained Lackeen at a
        later stage as John O’Kennedy is credited with the discovery of the ‘Stowe Missal’; tradition has it that it was
        hidden in the walls of Lackeen in the 18th century. This priceless manuscript is said to be one of the oldest books
        of its kind in Europe and is said to have been written in the 9th century at Ruadhan’s Abbey in Lorrha. The manuscript
        is held in the Royal Irish Academy and it’s beautifully jewel filled protective shrine is to be found in the National Museum.
    </string>
    <string name="textInformationredwoodcastle"> Situated by the Shannon banks, Redwood Castle was originally built by the
        Normans in the 12th century. The McEgans received the Castle from the O’Kennedys who took possession of it from the
        Normans. The Castle was reconstructed to its former glory by Michael McEgan in the 1970’s and is now open to the public.
        The McEgans were Brehons and bards to the O’Kennedys and a School of Law and History was held at the castle during
        the 16th and 17th centuries. Two famous students were educated here; they were Michael O’Cleary and Duald MacFirbis
        who were later to contribute to the writing of the ‘Annals of the Four Masters’. O’Cleary is said to have brought
        the unfinished book here in the mid 17th century to seek advice from McEgan. In the Confederate War of the 1640’s a
        leading Irish rebel, Rory O’Moore of Leix, suggested the printing of papers to help promote the Irish cause. He
        consulted one Constance McEgan of Redwood a move that wouldn’t have been to the McEgan’s favour when the Cromwellians
        arrived to quell the rebellion.
    </string>
    <string name="title_activity_maps_activity_redwood_castle">Map</string>


</resources>
